Guide to the East Flatbush and Prospect Lefferts Gardens Anti-Redlining records CBHM.0008
Center for Brooklyn History
East Flatbush and Prospect Lefferts Gardens Anti-Redlining records
1970-1989
Center for Brooklyn History
Gallagher, Philip F.
Gallagher, Mary A.Y.
CBHM.0008
4.5 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons and 1 legal manuscript box
This collection consists of material collected by Phil and Mary Gallagher during their participation in various community groups dedicated to fighting redlining in East Flatbush and Prospect Lefferts Gardens. The majority of materials come from Bank on Brooklyn, Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation, and Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush.
Historical Note
Bank on Brooklyn
Bank on Brooklyn (BOB) was formed in 1976 to work against redlining in the East Flatbush and Prospect Lefferts Gardens community. Early recruitment, organizational assistance, and data analysis was provided by the New York Public Interest Research Group, which was working out of Brooklyn College and had recently published Take the Money and Run: Redlining in Brooklyn, which served as early inspiration for the group. BOB formed several chapters in Brooklyn, including the founding chapter in East Flatbush and Prospect Lefferts Gardens (EFPLG). The group convinced several local banks (Greater New York Savings Bank, Independence Savings Bank, Dime Savings Bank, Flatbush Federal Savings and Loan, and Lincoln Savings Bank) to sign agreements committing to provide mortgages at reasonable rates to the EFPLG community. Banks also pledged to advertise their willingness to provide mortgages and to allow BOB to monitor their performance.
The Community Reinvestment Act (CRA), passed in 1977, obligates federally insured depository institutions to meet the credit needs of low and moderate income communities in a manner that is commensurate with sound lending practices. BOB used the CRA to challenge bank attempts to establish new branches outside of the EFPLG community. The group also pressured banks by collecting pledges from community members vowing to withdraw their money unless BOB demands were met. A mortgage hotline was established to field questions from community members about mortgages, financing, and their rights in dealing with banks and brokers. BOB also facilitated building inspections, met with bank regulatory agencies, and played a significant role in forming and supporting the Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush. BOB was later incorporated as Brooklyn Committee for Better Housing.
Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation
Founded in 1977, the Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation (FECDC) was formed to encourage and assist in the development, retention, and revitalization of local businesses. Funded by the New York City Office of Economic Development, the group also worked to aid, sponsor, and coordinate programs designed to eliminate or prevent residential or commercial blight. The FECDC oversaw several member organizations including the Vanderveer Estates Tenant Association, College Glen Community Association, and Avenue D Merchant Association. The group also worked to bring a chapter of Neighborhood Housing Services to East Flatbush.
Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush
In 1978, Congress established the Neighborhood Reinvestment Corporation (NRC), which provided initial grants for the development of Neighborhood Housing Services (NHS), a nationwide program to stimulate reinvestment in urban neighborhoods. In addition to funding, the NRC reviewed applications from local governments, conducted field reviews, and outlined agreements. A series of workshops were held to select partner cities and establish neighborhood boundaries. Once established, an NHS program operated as a private, nonprofit, tax-exempt community corporation. A neighborhood office and small staff oversaw home rehabilitation counseling, construction monitoring, and financial services. NHS also provided a revolving loan fund, which offered loans to residents who could not meet credit requirements necessary to secure a commercial loan.
At the urging of existing community groups, East Flatbush was selected as a division of NHS New York City. NHS of East Flatbush was overseen by a board of directors made up of local residents, bankers, and local and state government officials. In the first three years (1982-1985) they provided 44 loans totaling $340,000. The office also offered free technical assistance assessing home improvement needs, contract bids, and workshops such as front yard and strip beautification. As of 2023 NHS, of East Flatbush operates as NHS Brooklyn Community Development Corporation.
Biographical Note
Mary Gallagher graduated in 1967 from the University of Notre Dame with an M.A. in Latin American History and earned a Ph.D. in Latin American History from the Graduate School of the City University New York. She worked as a translator, transcriber, and later co-editor of The Papers of Robert Morris, a nine-volume documentary history of the finances and the diplomacy of American Revolution. Gallagher also served as assistant editor on The Papers of John Jay and taught undergraduate and graduate history courses at Hunter College, Brooklyn College, and Queens College.
Philip (Phil) Gallagher graduated in 1963 from the College of the Holy Cross with a B.A. in History, followed by an M.A. and Ph.D. in Medieval History from the University of Notre Dame. Gallagher taught Medieval History at Brooklyn College from 1967-2012 and served as the History Department Chair from 1995-2002.
Phil and Mary moved to East Flatbush in 1974, shortly after the birth of their daughter. The couple held several leadership positions in local groups, with Mary specializing in commercial strips, serving as Co-Director of Bank on Brooklyn and President of the Flatbush-East Development Corporation. Phil specialized in housing, serving as Co-Director of Bank on Brooklyn and Chairman of the Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush. After 15 years the couple stepped down from their roles in an effort to see the community's Black residents step into leadership positions.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in alphabetical order by folder title. Due to an unclear original order, arrangement has been imposed by the archivist to enhance discoverability.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 1, folder 21 is closed for research. See the Conditions Governing Access note at that level for more information. Other materials are open to researchers without restriction.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Phil and Mary Gallagher, 2022.
Related Materials
Arnie Goldwag Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) collection (ARC.002)
Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation Oral History collection (2008.030)
Brooklyn neighborhood associations and civic organizations publications (ARC.167)
Eastern Parkway Coalition records (2007.016)
Robert Thomason Prospect Lefferts Gardens Neighborhood Association (PLGNA) Collection (BCMS.0084)
Ronald Shiffman collection on the Pratt Center for Community Development (2013.023)
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of material collected by Phil and Mary Gallagher during their participation in various community groups dedicated to fighting redlining in East Flatbush and Prospect Lefferts Gardens. The majority of materials come from Bank on Brooklyn, Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation, and Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush, however, items from additional groups in Brooklyn and other boroughs are represented. Items from Neighborhood Housing Services of New York City have been foldered separately from items concerning the East Flatbush office. Unless otherwise noted, Bank on Brooklyn items represent Bank on Brooklyn of East Flatbush and Prospect Lefferts Gardens.
Materials from various groups concerning bank meetings, correspondence, and branch challenges have been foldered under the bank name. Monitoring forms, community reinvestment act statements, and clippings are also housed with their respective banks. These folders also contain testimonies from community group members. Materials from bank regulatory agencies and government offices are also foldered under the agency name and include correspondence, newsletters, reports, and notes.
Materials from Bank on Brooklyn, Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation, Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush, and additional groups include various committee meeting minutes, by-laws, correspondence, newsletters, and personnel information. Items concerning real estate visits, property rehabilitation, and financing are also included. Extensive handwritten notes appear in notebooks, loose papers, and on the backs of flyers and pledge cards. All notes are presumably by Phil and Mary Gallagher.
Please note that folders have been titled by the archivist to best represent the bulk of items stored within, however, there is significant overlap of groups and matters.
East Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Discrimination in housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing policy--New York (State)--New York; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Prospect Lefferts Gardens (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Discrimination in mortgage loans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Discrimination in banking |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Banks and banking |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Bank on Brooklyn: Brochure, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Clippings, Newsletters, Press Releases, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Community Meeting Agenda and Notes, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Community Reinvestment Act Committee, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Coordinating Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Correspondence, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Flyers, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Fundraising Dinner, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Bank in Brooklyn: Interviews with Community Members Re: Home Mortgages, circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Lending Analysis for Various Banks, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Membership Lists, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Monitoring Forms and Census Track Materials, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Mortgage Hotline Funding, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Photograph, circa 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Planning and Organizing, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Real Estate Visits and Questions, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Recruiting Committee, circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Songs, circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Steering Committee, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Bank on Brooklyn: Training Materials, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Bank Withdrawal Pledge Cards [RESTRICTED], circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Due to sensitive personal information, these materials are not open for research. Information from these materials can be requested on a case by case basis with a signed Center for Brooklyn History confidentiality agreement.
- Brooklyn Summit Conference on Racial/Ethnic Relations, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- California Redlining and Housing Information, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Carver Federal Savings and Loan Association: Bank on Brooklyn Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Center for Community Change: Anti-Steering Reference Materials, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Chicago Anti-Redlining and Housing Information, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Coalition Against Redlining: Hearings, Federal Reserve, Bank Closures, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 27-29)
- College Glen Community Association: 2044-2048 Nostrand Avenue, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- College Glen Community Association: Meeting Minutes, By-Laws, Notes, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- College Glen Community Association: Newsletters, Clippings, Flyers, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- College Glen Association: Notes, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- College Glen Association: Tenants Clinic and Workshop, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Community District 17 Census, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Community Reinvestment Act Regulations, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Community Training and Resource Center: Branch Bank Closing Study, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Contact Information (Organization Unknown), circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Department of Housing Preservation and Development Home Improvement Program, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Dime Savings Bank: Bank on Brooklyn Correspondence and Meeting Notes, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Dime Savings Bank: Community Reinvestment Act Statement, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Dime Savings Bank: Monitoring, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- East 39th Street Block Association: Meeting Agenda and Minutes, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- East Flatbush Banking Services Forum, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- European American Bank: Branch Closures, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- European American Bank: Community Reinvestment Act Statement, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Equal Credit Opportunity Act, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Erasmus Neighborhood Federation, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Federal Home Loan Bank Board, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Federal Reserve Bank of New York: Community Affairs Meeting, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Federal Reserve Bank of New York: Correspondence and Notes, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: After School Program Application, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: Avenue D Revitalization, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: Board of Directors, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: By Laws, circa 1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: Certificate of Incorporation (photocopy), circa 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: Correspondence, 1980-1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: Energy Home Improvement, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: Newsletters, Clippings, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: Nominating Committee, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: Nostrand Avenue Revitalization Project, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: Personnel, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Flatbush-East Community Development Corporation: Safe 17, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Flatbush Federal Savings and Loan: Bank in Brooklyn Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Flatbush Federal Savings and Loan: Community Reinvestment Act Statement, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Flatbush Federal Savings and Loan: Monitoring, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Flatbush Federal Savings and Loan / West Side Federal Savings and Loan: Merger, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Flatbush Federal Savings and Loan / West Side Federal Savings and Loan: Merger Testimonies, circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Glenwood Hall Tenants Association: Correspondence and Meeting Notes, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Greater New York Savings Bank: Advisory Committee on Home Lending, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Greater New York Savings Bank: Application Challenges, 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Greater New York Savings Bank: Avenue U Branch, 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Greater New York Savings Bank: Bank on Brooklyn Correspondence and Meeting Notes, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Greater New York Savings Bank: Clippings and Brochures, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Greater New York Savings Bank: Community Reinvestment Act Statement, circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Greater New York Savings Bank: Monitoring, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Greater New York Savings Bank: South Brooklyn Against Investment Discrimination, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Greenpoint-Williamsburg Committee Against Redlining: Press Release, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Home Mortgage Disclosure Act, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Housing and Urban Development: Correspondence, Notes, Summary, 1975-1981 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Independence Savings Bank: Bank on Brooklyn Correspondence and Meeting Notes, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Independence Savings Bank: Community Reinvestment Act Statement, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Jamaica Savings Bank: Application Protest, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Junction / College: Newsletters, Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Legislative Materials, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Lincoln Savings Bank: Bank on Brooklyn Correspondence, Press, Notes, 1975-1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Lincoln Savings Bank: Community Reinvestment Act Statement, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Manufacturers-Hanover Trust Company: Bank on Brooklyn Correspondence, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Massachusetts Redlining and Housing Information, 1979-1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Metropolitan Savings Bank: Bank on Brooklyn Correspondence and Meeting Notes, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Metropolitan Savings Bank: Building Inspections, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Metropolitan Savings Bank: Community Reinvestment Act Statement, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Metropolitan Savings Bank: Monitoring, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Metropolitan Savings Bank: Mortgage Disclosure Statement, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Metropolitan Savings Bank / Spring Valley Savings and Loan: Merger, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
- Monsonis vs. Best, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Mortgage Demands in East Flatbush and Prospect Lefferts Gardens, circa 1978 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Mortgage Information, General, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Mortgage Loan Data for Various Banks, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Multi Family Dwellings: Building Lists, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Multi Family Dwellings: Clippings, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Multi Family Dwellings: Rehabilitation and Financing, circa 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Multi Family Dwellings: Strategy, 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- National Bank of North America: Community Reinvestment Act Statement, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Neighborhood Housing Services: By Laws, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Neighborhood Housing Services: Central Board Nominating Committee, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Neighborhood Housing Services: Central and Neighborhood Board Members, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush: Board of Directors, 1981-1988 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush: Boundary Committee, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush: Committees, 1981-1988 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush: Community Relations Committee, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush: Convenors Committee, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush: Correspondence, 1981-1988 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush: Development Committee, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush: General Information, 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush: Newsletters, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush: Personnel, 1981-1987 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Neighborhood Housing Services of East Flatbush: Photographs, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Neighborhood Housing Services: Newsletters, Clippings, Reports, 1978-1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Neighborhood Housing Services: Other Cities, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Neighborhood Housing Services: Personnel, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
- Neighborhood Housing Services: Program Operations Committee, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Neighborhood Hosing Services: Recruitment and Work Plans, circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Neighborhood Housing Services: Structure and Business Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Neighborhood Housing Services: Site Recommendation Committee, circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Neighborhood Housing Services: Workshops, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- The New York Bank for Savings: Community Reinvestment Act Statement, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- New York Public Interest Research Group: Bank on Brooklyn, Citizens Alliance, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- New York State Banking Department: Correspondence, Reports, Statements, 1977-1984 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- New York State Banking Department: Press Release, Clippings, 1977-1981 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Newsletters from Various Organizations, 1979-1985 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Nostrand-Renaissance Tenants Association: Correspondence, Newsletter, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Notes and Speeches: General, 1977-1987 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Organizing and Facilitating: General Information, 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Petitions: Anti-Redlining, circa 1978 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Prospect Lefferts Gardens Neighborhood Association, 1976-1986 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Real Estate Broker Regulations, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Regional Interagency Committee Conference: Financial Services in the 80's, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Reports on Housing, Mortgages, Neighborhood Revitalization, 1977-1987 (Box 4, Folder 22-23)
- Reports on Housing, Mortgages, Neighborhood Revitalization, 1977-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- South Brooklyn Against Investment Discrimination: Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- South Brooklyn Against Investment Discrimination: Reports, 1977-1979 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- South Shore Bank: Community Reinvestment Act Statement, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- State of New York Mortgage Agency, 1978-1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Take the Money and Run: Redlining in Brooklyn, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- West Side Federal Savings and Loan: Bank on Brooklyn Correspondence and Meeting Notes, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- West Side Federal Savings and Loan: Mortgage Disclosures, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- WNET Thirteen: Just Around the Corner, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Vanderveer Estates Rehabilitation: Clippings, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Vanderveer Estates Rehabilitation: Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Vanderveer Estates Rehabilitation: Meeting Notes, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Vanderveer Estates Rehabilitation: Reports and Documents, 1980-1982 (Box 5, Folder 13)